本劇改編自聖經  它們曾改變世界
本劇將始終保持《聖經》真諦
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
退後
Back!
馬利亞  很快你將生下一子
Mary, you will soon give birth to a son-
神的兒子
the Son of God.
有星要出於雅各
A star shall come out of Jacob,
有杖要興於以色列
and a scepter shall rise out of lsrael.
我相信您的兒子必是其子民未來的王
I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什麼名字
What is his name?
耶穌
Jesus.
他的名字是耶穌
His name is Jesus.
即將到來的那一位  大過我
There is one to come greater than me.
我不過是曠野中的吶喊  做好準備迎接
I'm just a voice in the wilderness, preparing the way for the-
上帝
Lord.
起來  走走
Get up and walk.
這個來自加利利的擾亂者是個麻煩
This agitator from Galilee- he's trouble.
有人說那個耶穌把一個死人救活了
They say this Jesus has raised a man from the dead.
上帝會將他的忿怒降在所有人身上
God will bring his wrath down upon all of us,
誰知道彼拉多會做出什麼
and who knows what Pilate will do?
大人  有個猶太人最近在聖殿裡惹麻煩
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
你們不能侍奉主的同時  又侍奉金錢
You cannot serve God and money.
如果這場騷亂在第二天依然繼續的話
If the disturbances that took place today are repeated tomorrow,
我將立刻關閉聖殿
I will shut the tempie immediately.
毀了這殿  我會在三日之內重新建立起來
Destroy this temple, and I will build it again in three days.
他威脅說要拆毀聖殿
He threatens to destroy the temple.
我們得除掉他  否則羅馬人會毀滅一切
We remove this man, or the Romans destroy everything.
-處死  -沒錯
- Execute? - Yes.
犧牲這農夫的命  換取上帝之國的到來
The life of one peasant for the future of God's nation.
你必因此事後悔終生
You'lI live to regret this.
一周之後就沒人會記得他是誰了
He'll be forgotten in a week.
我的兒子
My son!
你們心裡固然願意  肉體卻太軟弱
The spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak.
父啊  赦免他們吧
Father! Forgive them,
因為他們並不知曉他們所作所為
for they know not what they do.
你去哪兒了  你本應是他的磐石
Where were you? You were supposed to be his rock.
我辜負了他  不敢請求他的原諒
I failed him. Now I can't ask him to forgive me.
馬利亞
Mary.
我來了
I am here.
聖經
彼得  彼得
Peter. Peter!
大家  墳墓打開了
Everyone. The tomb is open.
-他還活著  -什麼
- He's alive. - What?
我看見他了
I saw him.
那不可能
That's not possible.
不  我看見了
No. I saw him.
馬利亞  那可能是其他人
Mary, maybe it was someone else.
你們覺得我瘋了
You think I'm mad.
彼得  你去看看那墳墓吧
Peter, see the tomb for yourself.
求你了
Please.
彼得
Peter?
現在你相信了嗎
Now do you believe me?
但他走了
But he's gone.
走了
Gone?
不
No.
他回來了
He's back.
對  非常新鮮的餅哦
Yes, very fresh. The bread is fresh.
謝謝
Thank you.
杯子  我需要杯子和一點酒
A cup. I need a cup and some wine.
怎麼了
What happened?
他的身體
His body.
他的血
His blood.
我就是道路
I am the way,
真理
the truth...
生命
and the life.
不
No.
不  這不是真的
No, this isn't real.
主
Lord.
多馬
Thomas.
不要疑惑
Stop doubting...
總要信
and believe.
真的是你
It is you.
你因看見了我
Because you see me,
才信
you believe.
那沒有看見
Blessed are those...
就信的
who have not seen me...
有福了
and yet... have believed.
四十天之後
當聖靈降臨在你們身上
When the Holy Spirit comes to you,
你們就必得著能力
you'll receive power.
聖靈的力量
The power of the Holy Spirit...
能伴隨你們所有人  不論你們身在何處
can be with you all, wherever you are.
你們往普天下去
Go into the world...
傳福音給萬民聽
and preach the gospel to all creation.
願你們平安
Peace be with you.
距逾越節當天耶穌被釘在十字架上
It's 50 days since Passover-
已經過去50天了
the day Jesus was crucified.
如今成千上萬的猶太朝聖者來到耶路撒冷
Now thousands of Jewish pilgrims come to Jerusalem...
慶祝五旬節
for the festival of Pentecost.
必須是基督徒
Must be Christians.
有耶穌追隨者出現的跡象嗎
Any sign of Jesus' followers?
沒有
No.
我認為他們都已經回到加利利去了
I assume they've all gone back to Galilee.
你怎麼看
Do you?
讓你的人做好準備就可以了
Just make sure your men are ready.
如果他們回來了  你要對付他們
If they return, you have to deal with them.
我不能再煽動羅馬人一次
I cannot call upon the Romans again.
他在那
There he is.
司提反
Stephen.
你在這裡我們很高興  兄弟
We're glad you're here, brother.
往這邊走
This way.
我們還是小心點  他們在看著我們
We must be careful though. They're watching us.
約翰  你們都安全我很高興
John, I'm glad you're all safe.
又見到你很高興  司提反
It's good to see you again, Stephen.
馬太
Matthew.
它會以什麼形式出現
What form will it take?
它什麼時候來
When will it come?
耶穌說過我們要做的就是問
Jesus said all we had to do is ask.
我一直在問  每天都問
I have been asking. Every day.
恰當之時聖靈就會降臨
The Holy Spirit will come when the time is right.
我覺得我們應該共同祈禱
I think we should pray together.
我們在天上的父
Our Father, who is in heaven,
願人都尊你的名為聖
hallowed be your name.
願你的國降臨
Your kingdom come, your will be done,
願你的旨意行在地上  如同行在天上
on earth as it is in heaven.
我們日用的飲食  今日賜給我們
Give us this day our daily bread,
免我們的債
and forgive us our trespasses,
如同我們免了人的債
as we forgive those who trespass against us.
不叫我們遇見試探
And lead us not into temptation-
救我們脫離凶惡
but deliver us from evil.
發生什麼事了
What's happening?
看那風  看那雲
The wind! The clouds!
耶穌是救世主
先知曾預言過
他被釘上十字架  但是死而復生
耶穌是救世主
我見到他被釘上十字架
然後死而復生
頌贊歸於上帝
他被釘上十字架然後死而復生
跟隨猶太人
和所有居住在耶路撒冷的人們
耶穌是救世主
在天上我要顯出奇事  在地下我要顯出神跡
本字幕由YYeTs人人影視翻譯第一版
由Matt K Fu 以基督徒角度作編修
僅供學習 禁止用於任何商業盈利行為
翻譯：sakura櫻  桑尼君  賀天天  小琪777
翻譯：和小蟹  袋小待  茶炒栗子海倫
校對：威廉  sienna   時間軸：加森
後期：zzzyusa   總監：不要叫我馬維斯
我們是如何學會說那些語言的
How can we speak those languages?
是聖靈  他與我們同在
The Holy Spirit. He is with us.
謝謝  謝謝
Thank you. Thank you.
我的弟兄  來聽聽這些話
My brothers, come hear the word.
謝謝你  姑娘  謝謝
Thank you, sister. Thank you.
謝謝
Thank you.
馬利亞
Mary?
當聖靈降臨在你們身上
When the Holy Spirit comes to you,
你們就必得著能力
you'll receive power.
金銀我都沒有
I don't have silver or gold.
只把我所有的給你
But what I have I will give you.
我奉拿撒勒人耶穌基督的名
In the name of Jesus Christ,
我們的主和救主
our Lord and Savior,
叫你起來
rise up...
行走吧
and walk.
-快來看看  -怎麼了
- Come and see this. - Huh? Huh?
太神奇了
It's amazing.
你們覺得我們憑自己的能力使他痊愈了嗎
Do you think he is healed by our power?
是因為耶穌  他還沒死
It is through Jesus. He did not die.
他仍與我們同在
He is still with us.
是他的能力使這人行走
It is his power that made this man walk.
耶穌做到的
Jesus did this.
Jesus did this!
耶穌做到的  耶穌做到的
Jesus did this! Jesus did this!
耶穌做到的
Jesus did this!
耶穌
Jesus!
耶穌做到的
Jesus did this!
耶穌
Jesus!
耶穌做到的
Jesus did this!
耶穌做到的  耶穌
Jesus did this. Jesus!
耶穌做到的  耶穌做到的
Jesus did this! Jesus did this!
他們在說什麼
What are they saying?
他們又在喊那苦命男人的名字
They're shouting that wretched man's name again.
他們說他治好了那個乞丐
They say he cured the beggar.
把帶頭者抓來
Bring the ringleaders to me.
還有那個說謊的乞丐
And that lying beggar.
這邊
This way.
這裡  坐下
There. Sit down.
趴下  別動
Get down. Don't move.
他們今天有多少人反叛了
How many have they turned today?
估計有5000人
We think 5,000.
5000人
5,000.
告訴我
Tell me,
你為何覺得可以
why did you think it would be acceptable
以死去的異教徒之名傳福音
to preach in the name of a dead heretic?
耶穌沒有死
Jesus isn't dead.
他還活著
He lives.
他被處死了  他死了
He was executed. He is dead.
今天是耶穌基督的能力使這人能行走
This man walks today only through the power of Jesus Christ.
真的嗎
Really?
他生來就是跛子
He has been lame since birth.
行  我明白了
Yes. I see.
你不允許再提起這個乞丐
You are not allowed to speak of this beggar...
或者你死去的彌賽亞
or your dead Messiah...
從現在開始
from this moment on.
這是真理
It is the truth.
-提到他是我們的義務  -義務
- We have a duty to speak it. - Duty?
義務
Duty?
我的義務是
I have a duty...
我們的聖殿  我們的國家
to our temple, to our nation,
和我們的神
to our God!
我同時掌控律法
I also have the law.
我有能力
I have the power,
而且你也在我這兒
and I have you here.
你要麼沉默
You will be silent,
否則就讓你永遠沉默
or you will be silenced.
把他們帶走
Take them away.
來吧
Right, come on!
我們不懼死亡
We are not afraid of death.
奉耶穌基督的名受洗
Be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ.
叫你們的罪得赦
You can all be baptized for the forgiveness of your sins.
他被釘十字架  卻死裡復活
He was crucified, but he rose from the dead!
不可能的  不要聽信他
Impossibie! Don't listen to him.
你為何要抵擋耶穌
Why do you resist Jesus?
是他拯救了你
He is your Savior.
引導我們走永生的道路
The way to everlasting life!
耶穌死了
Jesus is dead!
而你將重蹈他的覆轍
And you'll go the same way.
-僭妄者  -不
- Blasphemer! - No!
耶穌還活著
Jesus is alive.
他們試圖殺了他  但失敗了
They tried to kill him, but they failed.
他是一位真正的先知
He is a true prophet.
是我們的彌賽亞
Our Messiah!
你對先知了解多少
What do you know about the prophets?
你所謂的先知將自己凌駕於律法之上
Your prophet put himself above the law.
這個男孩什麼都不知道
This boy knows nothing.
我讀過聖經
I know the Scriptures!
是嗎
Really?
那你應該知道申命記
Then you'll know Deuteronomy.
因為他試圖
Because he sought...
勾引你們離開耶和華  你們的神
to entice you away from the Lord. Your God,
"你要先下手
"Your hand shall be the first against him,
要用石頭
and you shall stone him with stones...
打死他"
until he dies!"
我看見天開了
I see the heavens opening.
人子站在神的右邊
And the Son of man standing at the right hand of God.
-大數的保羅  -是的  大祭司
- Paul of Tarsus. - Yes, High Priest.
今天的事件可能會引發暴動
That incident today could have started a riot.
他是個異教徒
He was a heretic.
他試圖引導我們的人民遠離上帝
He was trying to lead our peopie away from God.
罪有應得
He got what he deserved.
這是眾望所歸
It was the will of the people.
真的嗎
Was it really?
或許
Perhaps...
你和我
you and I...
可以一同為眾人了卻心願
might serve the people's will together.
我可以為你驅除這顆渣滓
I could flush this scum out for you,
但我需要幫助
but I need help.
你需要什麼幫助
What do you need?
人手
Men.
金錢
Money.
和你寫的介紹信
Letters of introduction from you.
馬勒古
Malchus.
我的人手隨你調配
My servant is at your disposal.
我們吃吧
Let us eat.
我們幸運地受惠-
We are blessed to receive-
兄弟姐妹們
Brothers and sisters.
主耶穌
Our Lord Jesus,
被賣的那一夜
on the night of his betrayal,
拿起餅來
took bread.
祝謝了  就擘開
And when he'd given thanks, he broke the bread.
歡迎你  朋友
Welcome. Friend.
請坐吧
Please.
坐下來和我們一起吃
Sit with us and eat.
相信我
Trust me,
我並不是你們的朋友
I am not your friend.
抓住他們
Take them.
走  走  走  快
Go, go, go. Quickly.
快  快跑
Go on, run away!
這邊
This way!
告訴你所有的朋友們
Tell all your friends,
所有耶穌的追隨者
all you followers of Jesus,
我  大數的保羅  會找到你們的
that I, Paul of Tarsus, will find you!
上帝
God...
與我同在
is on my side!
他們去哪了
Where did they go?
忽然間就沒人宣揚耶穌了
Suddenly no one's talking about Jesus.
我不相信他們會輕易背棄於他
I don't beileve they've just given up on him.
那
So...
他們去哪了
where are they?
我不知道  我發誓
I don't know. I swear.
大馬士革
Damascus.
有人提過要去大馬士革
Someone said Damascus.
真不知道他們為什麼要躲著我
I don't know why they run from me.
我使他們免於上帝的審判  他們本應感恩戴德
They should be grateful I'm saving them from God's judgment.
-他們還會敬畏上帝嗎  -根本不會
- Do they even care about God? - No.
他們離棄上帝於不顧
They abandoned God to follow
反而追隨這骯臟無知的渣滓
this dirty, uneducated scum.
繼續前進
Go on, hah!
你是誰
Who are you?
報上名來
Tell me who you are!
我就是你所迫害的耶穌
I am Jesus, whom you persecute.
不可能
No!
耶穌已死
Jesus is dead.
不可能  不可能
No! No!
我的眼睛  我瞎了
My eyes. I'm blind.
主
Lord?
亞拿尼亞
Ananias.
到那叫"直街"的路上去
Go to the street called Straight.
找一個大數人  名叫保羅
Ask for a man they call... Paul of Tarsus.
保羅
Paul?
但他與我們為敵
But he beats us.
他四處搜捕你的信徒
He arrests your followers everywhere.
他是我揀選的器皿  要把我的名
I have chosen him to proclaim my name to the world-
傳給外族人
to the gentiles,
君王
their kings...
和以色列人
and the sons of lsrael.
只管去吧
Go.
誰在那
Who's there?
你是誰
Who are you?
說話
Speak.
我是你要迫害的人之一
I am one of those you want to destroy.
請饒恕我
Forgive me.
是我錯冤了你們
I've wronged you.
是我誤解了上帝
I've wronged God.
我的靈魂已飽受煎熬
My soul is on fire.
請幫助我
Help me.
他是我揀選的器皿  宣揚我的名
I have chosen him to proclaim my name to the world.
主打發我來
I am sent by God.
叫你能看見
For you.
我認得你
I know you.
你去過我家
You came to my house.
不
No.
不  請別拋下我
No. No. Don't leave me.
No. Don't leave me.
我  亞拿尼亞
I, Ananias,
奉基督耶穌之名  為你  保羅  施洗
baptize you, Paul, in the name of Jesus Christ,
因你是他揀選的器皿  奉他的名改變世界
for he has chosen you to change the world in his name.
奉基督耶穌之名
In the name of Jesus Christ.
耶路撒冷
傳言大數人保羅的眼盲已經痊愈
They say that Paul of Tarsus has recovered from his blindness...
還成為了基督徒
and joined the Galileans.
我替您抓他回來
I'll find him for you.
然後如何
And then?
我要再遣人抓你回來嗎
Will I have to send someone after you?
不必了
No.
放他們去吧
Let them go.
如迦瑪列所言  人為之事
As Gamaliel said, if this is man's work,
必將潰敗
it will not succeed.
上帝之旨
If it is God's,
無以抗拒
we cannot fight it.
保羅的信仰改變了
Paul may have converted,
但世上仍有許多人想要鏟除耶穌的追隨者
but there are still many keen to stamp out Jesus' followers.
把他帶出來
Bring him out.
約翰的兄長  門徒雅各
The disciple James, brother of John,
被當權者逮捕
has been captured by the authorities.
約翰
John.
退後
Keep back.
不
No!
-冷靜  -把屍體處理掉
- Come on. - Get rid of him.
約翰
John.
聽我說  我們必須離開耶路撒冷
Come on. We must leave Jerusalem.
耶穌把我們帶來這裡
Jesus brought us here.
為我們...  送了命
He died here... for us.
太危險了
It is too dangerous.
要是我們留在這兒  都活不了
If we stay, we will all die.
我不畏懼死亡
I'm not afraid of death.
我們都不畏懼
None of us are.
但是多馬說得對
But Thomas is right.
要是我們死了  就無法為耶穌傳道
We can't speak of Jesus if we're dead.
一路平安  朋友們
Travel safely, my friends.
約翰  我知道和關愛之人別離很艱難
John, I know it is hard to part from the people you love,
但你並非孤身一人
but you are not alone.
永遠不會
You never will be.
很多事變了
Much has changed.
-你準備去哪兒  -可能去北邊吧
- Where will you go? - North probably.
去以弗所
To Ephesus.
祝你好運
Good luck.
我們定會再見的  彼得
We will meet again, Peter.
不是在人間  就是在天堂
On earth or in heaven.
門徒們從耶路撒冷出發
Driven from Jerusalem,
成為了傳教士
the disciples become missionarles-
也就是使徒
apostles-
將新信仰的種子傳遍五湖四海
spreading the seeds of a new faith far and wide.
保羅行的路最遠
No one goes further than Paul.
他讓地中海一帶上百人改變了信仰
He converts hundreds across the Mediterranean.
謝謝
Thank you.
不過他一直無法擺脫迫害別人的過去
But his previous life as a persecutor haunts him.
我是大數人保羅
Paul of Tarsus.
我們知道你是誰
We know who you are.
就是他
That's him.
我沒惡意
I mean you no harm.
我在大馬士革有朋友
I have friends in Damascus.
你去拜訪過他們
You paid them a visit.
狠狠地傷害了他們
You meant them plenty of harm.
我改過自新了
I've changed.
我曾經失明了  但現在又能看得真切了
I was blind. Now I can see.
騙子
Liar.
我以前那麼做是因為我確信自己是正確的
I did what I did because I was certain I was right.
確信自己了解上帝的...  心意
That I knew what God... wanted.
就像你們現在如此確信一般
As you are certain now.
然後耶穌來找我
But then Jesus came to me.
不是因為義憤或是裁決
Not in righteous anger or in judgment,
而是...
but...
以愛之名
in love.
若沒有愛  我們便算不得什麼
And without love, we are nothing.
愛是恆久忍耐
Love is-is patient.
又有恩慈
Love is kind.
愛是不嫉妒  不自誇
It is not jealous. It does not boast.
不張狂
It is not proud.
不計較人的過犯
It keeps no records of wrongs. It-It-
只喜歡真理
It rejoices with the truth.
凡事包容
It bears all things.
凡事相信
It believes all things.
凡事盼望
It hopes all things,
凡事忍耐
It endures all things.
現在常存的
When everything else disappears,
有信  有望  有愛這三樣
faith, hope and love remain.
其中最大的...
But the greatest of these...
是愛
is love.
你叫什麼名字
What is your name?
路加
Luke.
跟從我  路加
Come with me, Luke.
我無法獨自完成
I can't do this alone.
彼得
Peter.
你做了如此多
You have done so much.
我為你而驕傲  我得人的漁夫
I am proud of you, my fisher of men.
我的主
My Lord.
我做了你告訴我要做的
I've done what you told me.
我們在整個猶太傳你的福音
We preach your word throughout Judaea.
這只是個開始
That is just the beginning.
世上還有很多人...
There are many across the world...
會想要聽你傳播福音
who will want to hear you.
沒有你...
Without you,
那只...
it's just-
應羅馬的名義  把門打開
Open up in the name of Rome.
應門吧
Answer it.
記住
Remember.
大門向所有人敞開
The door is open to everyone.
你必須跟我們走
You must come with us.
百夫長哥尼流想要見你
Centurion Cornelius wants you.
記住  大門向所有人敞開
Remember. The door is open to everyone.
一位天使向我顯現...
An angel came to me...
讓我去找你
and told me to find you,
聆聽你所有要說的話
to listen to all you have to say.
求你  救贖我
Please. Save me.
我只是一個跟你們一樣的人
I'm just a man like you.
能救贖你的是耶穌
It's Jesus who can save you.
來
Come.
我...彼得
I, Peter,
為你施洗  哥尼流
baptize you, Cornelius,
以聖父  聖子
in the name of the Father, the Son...
聖靈的名義
and the Holy Spirit.
哥尼流是第一個
Cornelius is the first Roman
以基督之名受洗的羅馬人
to be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ.
-謝謝你  -不用謝
- Thank you. - You are welcome.
跟我來
Come with me.
所有人都跟我來
All of you.
每一個信奉基督的人
Everyone who believes in Jesus,
都會以他的名義得蒙寬恕
receive forgiveness in his name.
每一個人都是
Everyone.
彼得
Peter.
來跟從我
Come with me,
我要叫你得人如得魚一樣
and I will make you a fisher of men.
我們要做什麼
What are we going to do?
改變世界
Change the world.
二十年後
耶穌門徒們帶著福音
The disciples take the gospel
來到了世界上最大的城市
to the world's great cities-
安提阿  哥林多  羅馬
Antioch, Corinth, Rome-
為被壓迫的人們帶去希望
bringing hope to the oppressed.
我帶來了能夠使你們解脫痛苦的好消息
I bring good news that will relieve your suffering.
一位偉大夫子的消息
News of a great teacher.
耶穌基督
Jesus Christ.
對耶穌敞開心扉
Open your hearts to Jesus,
你們將得永生
and you will have everlasting life.
-過來  -把他帶走
- Come here! - Get him out of there!
然而  宣揚一個新國度的到來
But preaching of a new kingdom
讓掌權者們感到了威脅
threatens those in power.
你是誰
Who are you?
兄弟姐妹們
Brothers and sisters,
我們要以患難為榮
we rejoice in our suffering-
因為我們知道
because we know that suffering...
患難產生忍耐
produces perseverance,
忍耐產生毅力
perseverance creates character...
毅力產生盼望
and character... hope.
基督教傳統中  十二使徒全都
Christian tradition says all the disciples
以身殉道
die for their cause.
彼得在羅馬被倒釘十字架而死
Peter is crucified in Rome upside down.
馬太在埃提阿伯被害
Matthew is killed in Ethiopia,
多馬死於印度南部
Thomas in southern India...
約翰在羅馬被灌毒
and John is poisoned in Rome.
保羅
Paul.
有人來抓你了
They're coming for you.
拿好了  總得有什麼留傳下去
Take these. Something must survive.
如果我死了
If not me,
那就讓我的話留傳下去
then my words at least.
走吧  你走吧
Go. Go.
我打了一場漂亮的仗
I fought a good fight.
我完成了使命
I finished the race.
我信主不曾動搖
And I kept the faith.
保羅被羅馬人斬首處決
Paul is beheaded by the Romans,
但他所說的話得以留傳
but his words live on.
《新約》中近一半的內容是他寫的書信
His letters form nearly half of the New Testament.
但最終章才剛剛開始
But the final chapter is yet to be written.
羅馬人沒能毒死約翰
The Romans fail to kill John.
他們受了挫  就把他流放到
In frustration, they exile him
希臘的一處流放地
to a penal colony in Greece.
一個名叫拔摩的海島
An island called Patmos.
約翰在這裡度過了余生
Here, John lives out his days...
寫下了《啟示錄》
and writes Revelation,
《聖經》的最後一本書
the last book of the Bible.
世人們
The people today-
稱你為王
they called you king.
他們認為你是彌賽亞
They think you are the Messiah.
你們認為我是誰
Who do you think I am?
你是神的兒子
You are the Son of God.
倘若他不是彌賽亞呢
What if he's not the one?
我們以身犯險  是為了什麼
We're risking our lives. For what?
他已經向我們展示了能力
He has shown us his power.
我們要對他有信心
We must have faith in him.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
要相信上帝
Trust in God.
也要相信我
Trust in me also.
我要去的地方  你們認得那條路
You know the way to where I'm going.
我們不知道你往哪裡去
We don't know where you're going.
怎麼認得那條路呢
How can we know the way?
我就是路
I am the way,
真理
the truth...
和生命
and the life.
我是阿拉法
I am the alpha...
我是俄梅格
and the omega.
我是首先的
The first...
也是末後的
and the last.
我是創始的
The beginning...
也是成終的
and the end.
主啊
My Lord.
我一直在等待死亡的降臨
I had been expecting death to come.
不再有死亡
There will be no more death...
也不再有悲哀  哭號
or mourning or crying...
痛苦
or pain.
我將一切都更新了
I am making everything new.
是的
Yes.
我必快來
I am coming soon.
願主的恩惠
May the grace of the Lord...
常與神的人民同在
be with all God's people.
阿們
Amen.